<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-01-14T14:58:23-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fear God &amp;amp; Dreadnought</title><subtitle>Essays and commentary on naval history, policy, and technology, past, present, and future.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Loss of Force Z (on this day in history)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/12/10/The-Loss-of-Force-Z-(on-this-day-in-history).html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Loss of Force Z (on this day in history)" /><published>2018-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/12/10/The-Loss-of-Force-Z-(on-this-day-in-history)</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/12/10/The-Loss-of-Force-Z-(on-this-day-in-history).html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/Images/Painting1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;An artist’s rendition of &lt;em&gt;Prince of Wales&lt;/em&gt; (left) and &lt;em&gt;Repulse&lt;/em&gt; (right) under attack by Japanese aircraft.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
                On this day in 1941, just three days after the attack on Pearl Harbor, Japanese land-based aircraft sank the &lt;em&gt;Renown&lt;/em&gt; class battlecruiser &lt;em&gt;Repulse&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;King-George-V&lt;/em&gt; class battleship &lt;em&gt;Prince of Wales&lt;/em&gt; in the South-China Sea. While the men of Force Z fought valiantly to repel the Japanese aircraft and avoid their torpedoes and bombs, both capital ships ultimately succumbed to the aerial onslaught, with hundreds of casualties; even worse, of eighty-eight Japanese aircraft involved in the attack, only four were destroyed (using figures from Wikipedia). Somewhat ironically, this triumph of aircraft over some of the Royal Navy’s best capital ships was likely just as, if not more troublesome to the Japanese than the British. While the British were evidently shocked that a modern battleship and modernized battlecruiser had been sunk in open ocean by aircraft (even worse in their eyes, by Japanese pilots), the victory had serious implications for Japan’s naval strategy and tactics. Had the IJN not just spent the prior decade designing and building the largest, most-powerfully armed and best-protected class of fast-battleships in the world? With the explicit intent of giving the IJN the decisive edge in the decisive battle they planned to fight against the American battle line, which at best they could attrit through airstrikes? Did the sinking of Repulse and Prince of Wales, capable warships of the British Empire, not imply the same fate could befall the ships of the &lt;em&gt;Yamato&lt;/em&gt; class? I am currently reading John Toland’s &lt;em&gt;The Rising Sun: The Decline and Fall of the Japanese Empire, 1936-45&lt;/em&gt;, in which the events of 10 December, 1941, are described in great detail; with the above questions in mind, I find it extraordinarily interesting to consider the effects of this action on the Japanese Naval leadership. While not as well known in the United States as the events of December 7, I think the attack on Force Z on December 10, 1941, and the courage displayed by the men involved, are deserving of our remembrance. Below is a poem I wrote on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“An Ode to Force Z”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Twas 10 December ‘41,
Two dreadnoughts underway;
Their mission: show the Rising Sun, 
That Britain still held sway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their names were H.M.S Repulse,
A swift, sleek battlecruiser,
And young and mighty Prince of Wales, 
Completed ten months prior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combined they formed the fast Force Z, 
Destroyers at their sides;
Their nakedness they failed to see, 
Through fog of hubris; pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those pesky birds just came and came, 
No heed the hail of fire;
Their engines buzzed like angry bees, 
A swarm never to tire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For then Repulse failed to Repulse, 
The fish that struck below;
Torpedoes struck, her hull convulsed, 
And so went down Repulse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prince of Wales was next to go, 
She lived a year then died;
Her loss was quite the savage blow, 
To British naval pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could those men have lost such face? 
To such a damned inferior race?
Their ships had ruled the waves for years, 
Yet there stood Churchill, eyes in tears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trafalgar’s spell had done them in, 
Superbia the fatal sin;
For Nelson’s glory, admirals yearned, 
Those poor brave fools, they’d never learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: 
&lt;em&gt;Kaigun: Strategy, Tactics, and Technology in the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1887-1941&lt;/em&gt;, by Evans and Peattie&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Rising Sun: The Decline and Fall of the Japanese Empire, 1936-45&lt;/em&gt; by John Toland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinking_of_Prince_of_Wales_and_Repulse&quot;&gt;Sinking of &lt;em&gt;Prince of Wales&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Repulse&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless otherwise stated, no images on this site are my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copyright © feargodanddreadnought.com. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An artist’s rendition of Prince of Wales (left) and Repulse (right) under attack by Japanese aircraft.                 On this day in 1941, just three days after the attack on Pearl Harbor, Japanese land-based aircraft sank the Renown class battlecruiser Repulse and King-George-V class battleship Prince of Wales in the South-China Sea. While the men of Force Z fought valiantly to repel the Japanese aircraft and avoid their torpedoes and bombs, both capital ships ultimately succumbed to the aerial onslaught, with hundreds of casualties; even worse, of eighty-eight Japanese aircraft involved in the attack, only four were destroyed (using figures from Wikipedia). Somewhat ironically, this triumph of aircraft over some of the Royal Navy’s best capital ships was likely just as, if not more troublesome to the Japanese than the British. While the British were evidently shocked that a modern battleship and modernized battlecruiser had been sunk in open ocean by aircraft (even worse in their eyes, by Japanese pilots), the victory had serious implications for Japan’s naval strategy and tactics. Had the IJN not just spent the prior decade designing and building the largest, most-powerfully armed and best-protected class of fast-battleships in the world? With the explicit intent of giving the IJN the decisive edge in the decisive battle they planned to fight against the American battle line, which at best they could attrit through airstrikes? Did the sinking of Repulse and Prince of Wales, capable warships of the British Empire, not imply the same fate could befall the ships of the Yamato class? I am currently reading John Toland’s The Rising Sun: The Decline and Fall of the Japanese Empire, 1936-45, in which the events of 10 December, 1941, are described in great detail; with the above questions in mind, I find it extraordinarily interesting to consider the effects of this action on the Japanese Naval leadership. While not as well known in the United States as the events of December 7, I think the attack on Force Z on December 10, 1941, and the courage displayed by the men involved, are deserving of our remembrance. Below is a poem I wrote on the subject.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Battlecruisers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/09/01/On-Battlecruisers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Battlecruisers" /><published>2017-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/09/01/On-Battlecruisers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/09/01/On-Battlecruisers.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/Images/965f69df2d96456252426c2f89f2f006.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The battlecruiser &lt;em&gt;Hood&lt;/em&gt;. Sleek, swift, and beautiful, she was the pride of the Royal Navy in the interwar period.&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
      Today, I’d like to discuss a type of warship surrounded with controversy: the battlecruiser. The British Royal Navy lost three of these majestic warships at the Battle of Jutland in 1916: The &lt;em&gt;Indefatigable&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Queen Mary&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Invincible&lt;/em&gt; (with Rear Admiral Horace Hood aboard) all blew up with almost no survivors. Years later, in 1941, the HMS &lt;em&gt;Hood&lt;/em&gt;, Britain’s last and most advanced battlecruiser, was lost in the Battle of the Denmark Strait–blowing up just as violently as her predecessors sunk at Jutland.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Something was evidently wrong with these “bloody” ships.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/Images/QueenMary1916.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The battlecruiser &lt;em&gt;Queen Mary&lt;/em&gt;, sunk at the Battle of Jutland in 1916.&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
      Many have concluded that the loss of these four vessels irrefutably demonstrated that the concept of the battlecruiser was unsound. As I see it, this is a misleading conclusion–the heavy losses sustained by the British at Jutland can much more accurately be attributed to the manner in which the ships were deployed and handled, rather than to any inherent flaws in the designs.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Nonetheless, the battlecruiser, with the armor of a cruiser but the guns and engines of a dreadnought battleship, was inherently unfit to serve in the line of battle, and the concept that these vessels could join into the line of battle after spotting the enemy fleet and reporting its position to the main body of their force was, without a doubt, problematic. But, without going into too much detail, allow me to pose a different argument, that the battlecruiser was an ideal warship for the protection of British commerce across the globe–that there was no financially better option. In &lt;em&gt;British Battlecruiser vs. German Battlecruiser&lt;/em&gt;, naval historian Mark Stille argues that the capital required for the British to procure a single battlecruiser could have been much better spent on a larger number of smaller cruisers.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; While he may be right, I would like to provide a different perspective.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/Images/NewZealand1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Indefatigable&lt;/em&gt; class battlecruiser &lt;em&gt;New Zealand&lt;/em&gt;, present at Jutland.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
      At the end of the 19th century, the Royal Navy’s numerical and qualitative superiority was unquestionable; the French, realizing they could never defeat the British in a major fleet engagement, decided to invest in the construction of a large number of armored cruisers which, in the event of war with Great Britain, could harass British commerce across the globe, crippling their economy. However, with the advent of the steam turbine, the age of the armored cruiser was coming to an end–it was now possible (albeit at great expense) to build a ship with the speed of a cruiser and the armament of a dreadnought battleship, although armor would have to be sacrificed in order to conserve weight. This class, the battlecruiser, would theoretically be able to outgun anything it couldn’t outrun (although as stated previously, this makes little sense in a line of battle or against other battlecruisers), and rendered all armored cruisers obsolete; the ability of the battlecruiser to intercept and destroy armored cruisers was amply demonstrated when &lt;em&gt;Invincible&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Inflexible&lt;/em&gt; sank &lt;em&gt;Scharnhorst&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Gneisenau&lt;/em&gt; at the Falklands in 1914. No standard cruiser could have performed the task as well.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/Images/Derfflinger2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;A drawing of &lt;em&gt;Derfflinger&lt;/em&gt;. Capable of speeds in excess of 25 knots, the &lt;em&gt;Derfflinger&lt;/em&gt; class nonetheless had an armored belt reaching a maximum thickness of 12 inches and an armament of eight 12in/50 guns. As stated by Stille, “These were arguably the best battlecruisers to see action during the war and came closest to being fast battleships” (Stille 42).&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
      So, was the battlecruiser concept a sound one, and were they worth the investment? Yes, and no. The battlecruiser was extremely effective at destroying enemy cruisers, and while used in this role would only be put at serious risk if used in battle against another vessel of its type; with this in mind, which other nations besides for Germany and the United States could actually afford to build and operate a sizeable fleet of battlecruisers? Although much has been written on the superiority of German battlecruisers to their British counterparts, and these German vessels proved quite useful in the major fleet actions of the war (Dogger Bank, Jutland), there was little or nothing they could do to prevent the British battlecruisers from operating with impunity across the globe, for they could not sail around the English Isles or through the English Channel into the North Sea without risking interception and annihilation by the Grand Fleet under Admiral Jellicoe. Thus, I would posit that the battlecruiser was, in many ways, quite a useful asset and arguably even an ideal instrument of seapower for the British Royal Navy prior to and during the First World War.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/Images/Derfflinger2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;A photo of &lt;em&gt;Derfflinger&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless otherwise stated, no images on this site are my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copyright © feargodanddreadnought.com. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Select Bibliography:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill, Richard. &lt;em&gt;War at Sea in the Ironclad Age&lt;/em&gt;. General editor John Keegan. London: Cassell &amp;amp; Co, 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Massie, Robert. &lt;em&gt;Castles of Steel: Britain, Germany, and the Winning of the Great War at Sea&lt;/em&gt;. London and New York: Random House, 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stille, Mark. &lt;em&gt;British Battlecruiser vs. German Battlecruiser: 1914-1916&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford: Osprey, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While the circumstances of &lt;em&gt;Hood&lt;/em&gt;’s sinking were quite different from those of her predecessors at Jutland, her destruction by the German battleship &lt;em&gt;Bismarck&lt;/em&gt; has hammered into societal consciousnessnes the notion that the idea of the battlecruiser was entirely unsound and that these ships were all liable to catastrophically blow up due to their lighter protection. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Following the catastrophic explosions of &lt;em&gt;Indefatigable&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Queen Mary&lt;/em&gt; at Jutland, Admiral David Beatty, commander of the Royal Navy’s 1st Battlecruiser Squadron, was told by a signalman on his flagship &lt;em&gt;Lion&lt;/em&gt; that the battlecruiser &lt;em&gt;Princess Royal&lt;/em&gt; had also blown up. With incredible sangfroid in the midst of such a heated action, Beatty stated that “there seems to be something wrong with our bloody ships today” (Massie, 596). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As described by historian Robert K. Massie in &lt;em&gt;Castles of Steel: Britain,Germany, and the Winning of the Great War at Sea&lt;/em&gt;, “No one in Britain or Germany had realized the menace of an explosive flash fire within an enclosed gun-turret system. In &lt;em&gt;Lion&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Seydlitz&lt;/em&gt;, and their sisters in both fleets, shells and powder journeyed upward on hoists from the magazines, through the turret lobbies, and into the turrets to the breeches of the guns. These separate compartments remained open and unsealed. A flash fire at any point along this extended route could spread quickly to all other points, including the magazines. Such a fire had occurred in &lt;em&gt;Lion&lt;/em&gt; at the Dogger Bank and might easily have destroyed her. The fire in her A turret lobby, which caused most of her casualties, could have spread downward into her ammunition handling rooms and from there into her magazines, where a cataclysmic explosion would have destroyed the ship. Fortunately, little ammunition was present in the turret lobby and the resulting fire was small and rapidly extinguished. As a result of this escape, the intrinsic danger of fire transmission went unrecognized on board the ship and at the Admiralty and no effort was made to install antiflash devices in turret trunks to prevent flames from spreading. Not until after Jutland sixteen months later, when the battlecruisers &lt;em&gt;Queen Mary&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Invincible&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Indefatigable&lt;/em&gt; blew up from this cause, were these corrections made in British ships” (Massie 419). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As written by Stille, “The question remains—was the battlecruiser effective? To answer this, the missions of the battlecruiser need to be kept in mind. These can be boiled down to protecting trade and acting as the main scouts for the battle fleet. In reality, these missions could have been carried out by an armoured cruiser with a standard 9.2 inch armament. Fisher’s demand for an all-big-gun ship with high speed was flawed from the start, since once assigned to the battle fleet as a scout, it would inevitably be used as any other capital ship. Once employed in such a manner, its lighter scale of protection was bound to jeaopardize its survival. It also must be pointed out that battlecruisers were much more expensive to build than battleships and had increased demands for machinery” (Stille, 76). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The battlecruiser Hood. Sleek, swift, and beautiful, she was the pride of the Royal Navy in the interwar period.       Today, I’d like to discuss a type of warship surrounded with controversy: the battlecruiser. The British Royal Navy lost three of these majestic warships at the Battle of Jutland in 1916: The Indefatigable, Queen Mary, and Invincible (with Rear Admiral Horace Hood aboard) all blew up with almost no survivors. Years later, in 1941, the HMS Hood, Britain’s last and most advanced battlecruiser, was lost in the Battle of the Denmark Strait–blowing up just as violently as her predecessors sunk at Jutland.1 Something was evidently wrong with these “bloody” ships.2 The battlecruiser Queen Mary, sunk at the Battle of Jutland in 1916.       Many have concluded that the loss of these four vessels irrefutably demonstrated that the concept of the battlecruiser was unsound. As I see it, this is a misleading conclusion–the heavy losses sustained by the British at Jutland can much more accurately be attributed to the manner in which the ships were deployed and handled, rather than to any inherent flaws in the designs.3 Nonetheless, the battlecruiser, with the armor of a cruiser but the guns and engines of a dreadnought battleship, was inherently unfit to serve in the line of battle, and the concept that these vessels could join into the line of battle after spotting the enemy fleet and reporting its position to the main body of their force was, without a doubt, problematic. But, without going into too much detail, allow me to pose a different argument, that the battlecruiser was an ideal warship for the protection of British commerce across the globe–that there was no financially better option. In British Battlecruiser vs. German Battlecruiser, naval historian Mark Stille argues that the capital required for the British to procure a single battlecruiser could have been much better spent on a larger number of smaller cruisers.4 While he may be right, I would like to provide a different perspective. Indefatigable class battlecruiser New Zealand, present at Jutland.       At the end of the 19th century, the Royal Navy’s numerical and qualitative superiority was unquestionable; the French, realizing they could never defeat the British in a major fleet engagement, decided to invest in the construction of a large number of armored cruisers which, in the event of war with Great Britain, could harass British commerce across the globe, crippling their economy. However, with the advent of the steam turbine, the age of the armored cruiser was coming to an end–it was now possible (albeit at great expense) to build a ship with the speed of a cruiser and the armament of a dreadnought battleship, although armor would have to be sacrificed in order to conserve weight. This class, the battlecruiser, would theoretically be able to outgun anything it couldn’t outrun (although as stated previously, this makes little sense in a line of battle or against other battlecruisers), and rendered all armored cruisers obsolete; the ability of the battlecruiser to intercept and destroy armored cruisers was amply demonstrated when Invincible and Inflexible sank Scharnhorst and Gneisenau at the Falklands in 1914. No standard cruiser could have performed the task as well. A drawing of Derfflinger. Capable of speeds in excess of 25 knots, the Derfflinger class nonetheless had an armored belt reaching a maximum thickness of 12 inches and an armament of eight 12in/50 guns. As stated by Stille, “These were arguably the best battlecruisers to see action during the war and came closest to being fast battleships” (Stille 42).       So, was the battlecruiser concept a sound one, and were they worth the investment? Yes, and no. The battlecruiser was extremely effective at destroying enemy cruisers, and while used in this role would only be put at serious risk if used in battle against another vessel of its type; with this in mind, which other nations besides for Germany and the United States could actually afford to build and operate a sizeable fleet of battlecruisers? Although much has been written on the superiority of German battlecruisers to their British counterparts, and these German vessels proved quite useful in the major fleet actions of the war (Dogger Bank, Jutland), there was little or nothing they could do to prevent the British battlecruisers from operating with impunity across the globe, for they could not sail around the English Isles or through the English Channel into the North Sea without risking interception and annihilation by the Grand Fleet under Admiral Jellicoe. Thus, I would posit that the battlecruiser was, in many ways, quite a useful asset and arguably even an ideal instrument of seapower for the British Royal Navy prior to and during the First World War. A photo of Derfflinger. While the circumstances of Hood’s sinking were quite different from those of her predecessors at Jutland, her destruction by the German battleship Bismarck has hammered into societal consciousnessnes the notion that the idea of the battlecruiser was entirely unsound and that these ships were all liable to catastrophically blow up due to their lighter protection. &amp;#8617; Following the catastrophic explosions of Indefatigable and Queen Mary at Jutland, Admiral David Beatty, commander of the Royal Navy’s 1st Battlecruiser Squadron, was told by a signalman on his flagship Lion that the battlecruiser Princess Royal had also blown up. With incredible sangfroid in the midst of such a heated action, Beatty stated that “there seems to be something wrong with our bloody ships today” (Massie, 596). &amp;#8617; As described by historian Robert K. Massie in Castles of Steel: Britain,Germany, and the Winning of the Great War at Sea, “No one in Britain or Germany had realized the menace of an explosive flash fire within an enclosed gun-turret system. In Lion, Seydlitz, and their sisters in both fleets, shells and powder journeyed upward on hoists from the magazines, through the turret lobbies, and into the turrets to the breeches of the guns. These separate compartments remained open and unsealed. A flash fire at any point along this extended route could spread quickly to all other points, including the magazines. Such a fire had occurred in Lion at the Dogger Bank and might easily have destroyed her. The fire in her A turret lobby, which caused most of her casualties, could have spread downward into her ammunition handling rooms and from there into her magazines, where a cataclysmic explosion would have destroyed the ship. Fortunately, little ammunition was present in the turret lobby and the resulting fire was small and rapidly extinguished. As a result of this escape, the intrinsic danger of fire transmission went unrecognized on board the ship and at the Admiralty and no effort was made to install antiflash devices in turret trunks to prevent flames from spreading. Not until after Jutland sixteen months later, when the battlecruisers Queen Mary, Invincible, and Indefatigable blew up from this cause, were these corrections made in British ships” (Massie 419). &amp;#8617; As written by Stille, “The question remains—was the battlecruiser effective? To answer this, the missions of the battlecruiser need to be kept in mind. These can be boiled down to protecting trade and acting as the main scouts for the battle fleet. In reality, these missions could have been carried out by an armoured cruiser with a standard 9.2 inch armament. Fisher’s demand for an all-big-gun ship with high speed was flawed from the start, since once assigned to the battle fleet as a scout, it would inevitably be used as any other capital ship. Once employed in such a manner, its lighter scale of protection was bound to jeaopardize its survival. It also must be pointed out that battlecruisers were much more expensive to build than battleships and had increased demands for machinery” (Stille, 76). &amp;#8617;</summary></entry></feed>